Register of the Superior Board of Underwriters Records, 1900-1933
Wisconsin Historical Society
Superior Board of Underwriters Records, 1900-1933
Superior Board of Underwriters (Superior, Wis.)
Superior Mss D
0.8 c.f. (2 archives boxes)
Housed at the Area Research Center, Jim Dan Hill Library, University of Wisconsin-Superior; owned by the Wisconsin Historical Society, Library-Archives Division
Records of the Board of Underwriters, an organization of Superior area fire and casualty insurance agents established to maintain equitable insurance rates. Included are proceedings, correspondence, financial records, and administrative materials including information on rates and insurance law. Much of the correspondence concerns the activities of Robert B. Nye, and the ouster of Charles A. Erhart in 1918. The Board was originally known as the Superior Fire Underwriters Association.
After being founded as the Superior Fire Underwriters' Association (1901-1908), the Superior, Wisconsin Board of Underwriters incorporated on June 11, 1908 with the stated purpose of joining local fire and casualty insurance agents in an organization to establish and maintain adequate and equitable rates of fire insurance. Each insurance agent was required to represent at least two stock companies and to pledge all his insurance brokerage business with Board members. Four constitutional officers and a Board of Directors presided over the business of the Board. Committees were appointed on membership, finance, arbitration and improvement, fire protection, and legislation. The position of solicitor was instituted to be responsible for renewals and the collection of premiums. Except for correspondence there are no records for the Board after 1930. The Board, apparently, dissolved in 1933.
The Records consist of constitutions, by-laws, and resolutions; proceedings; financial records; correspondence; and miscellaneous administrative papers directly concerning the Board of Underwriters. The materials have been arranged by type of record and chronologically thereunder.
The Proceedings file includes the minutes of the meetings of the Superior Fire Underwriters Association, ugust 13, 1900-May 11, 1908, and its successor, the Superior Board of Underwriters, July 14, 1908-April 25, 1919. Also included are minutes of the meetings of the Board of Directors, August 14, 1916-January 27, 1933, much of which is handwritten in rough note form.
Filed with the Financial Records of the Board are statements and invoices, 1913-1926, which include some correspondence, in particular relating to notification by various insurance companies of grain lines open in 1915. There is also a Treasurer's Cash Book, 1901-1916, recording cash transactions of the Board with date of payment, payor and assessment of payee and purpose, voucher number, and amount. The back of the volume contains a membership fee account, 1908-1909, and a special account, 1908-1916, kept by B. S. Loney, Trustee. Also in this file are bank deposit books, 1913-1926; check stub books, 1914-1926; and (stock?) certificate stub books, 1908-1909.
The Correspondence file consists of correspondence of the Superior Fire Underwriters' Association, 1901-1908, and the Superior Board of Underwriters, 1908-1933 (primarily 1908-1919), concerning policy, proxies, financial matters, and legislative information and queries. Also included are commentaries on resolutions and circular letters. Much of the material in this file deals with the activities of Robert B. Nye, and the ouster proceedings of Charles A. Erhart in 1918.
Administrative/Restriction Information
Transferred from the Douglas County Records in the State Archives, September 22, 1965. Records were originally donated by Mr. Newton of Superior on October 27, 1953, and held in the Ashland Regional Depository at Northland College until their transfer to the Manuscripts Division of the State Historical Society at Madison on September 22, 1965, as more properly manuscripts than archives of Douglas County.
Contents List
- Constitutions, By-Laws, and Resolutions (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Proceedings
  - August 13, 1900-May 11, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - July 17, 1908-May 21, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - May 28, 1912-April 25, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors' Minutes, August 14, 1916-January 27, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Financial Records
  - Financial Statements, Invoices, Records, 1902-1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer's Cash Book, 1901-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bank Deposit Books; Cash Stub Books, 1913-1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - (Stock?) Certificate Stubs, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence
  - January 16, 1901-December 9, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - July 17, 1908-August 11, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - April 21, 1914-December 21, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - January 11, 1915-December 12, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Applications for Membership; Solicitor Appointments, 1908-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Receipts for Rate Cabinets, October 1913 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Reports, Permits, Insurance Laws, and Rate Information (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Printed Materials, B-W (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 9)